A Guide to Papers Pertaining to Thomas Jefferson, Thomas Mann Randolph, and Monticello, 1791-1821
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers Pertaining to Thomas Jefferson, Thomas Mann Randolph, and Monticello 1791-1821
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12858
Ca. 35 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the University of Virginia Library from William Reese, New Haven, Connecticut, on November 4, 2003.
Scope and Content
These papers, 1791-1821, ca. thirty-five (35) items, pertain chiefly to the interest of Thomas Jefferson and Thomas Mann Randolph, in agricultural and scientific matters, and politics. Only two financial items are in Jefferson's hand; most are presumed to be in the hand of Thomas Mann Randolph.
Contents List
- Weather Records, kept by [Thomas Mann Randolph], in the format recommended by Thomas Jefferson in a letter, 1790 April 18 (not present), noting the temperature and barometric pressure twice a day. He also noted other "indexes of climate" such as the flowering of plants, the arrival of birds, and insects. 1791 March-1793
- Draft political essay by [Thomas Mann Randolph?] in the guise of a letter from an American in Amsterdam to the editor of the Patriote Francois attempting to disassociate the American people form the anti-republican views expressed by Gouverneur Morris, the American minister to France. 1792 April 8
- Draft resolution in defense of the Constitution from threats by proponents of British and monarchical principles by [Thomas Mann Randolph?] [1793 summer]
- Agricultural memoranda including a system of cultivation to be put in practice at Edgehill Farm containing 1575 acres, with a diagram showing the possible rotation of crops from 1795-1802 and an estimate of the probable crop of any one year; a neat chart with an explanation of signs and abbreviations for the years 1794-1801; a chart based on a six year rotation method; observations on Mr. Jefferson's system of rotation; a chart based on an eight year rotation method and dated 1793-1800; note about Monticello dated 1793 Jul 7 and a note about red clover. ca. 1793-1794
- [Thomas Mann Randolph ?] to the editor of an unidentified newspaper in response to "A Virginian's defense of the President [Washington]," saying that the President has deviated from his former path and shows too much attachment to British and monarchical principles. [ca. 1795?]
- Thomas Jefferson order for goods from James Leitch in Jefferson's hand, including wash basins, pitchers, chamber pots, and pepper. 1820 September 28
- Thomas Jefferson order for goods from James Leitch in Jefferson's hand, including cloth, lining and trimmings for two suits for servants. 1821 June 21
- Plan of Varina - View of the Buildings; Varina was a 950-acre plantation on the James River below Richmond, in Henrico County, Virginia. The diagram lists a dwelling house, barn, kitchen, overseers kitchen, foreman's house, smith shop, dairy, smoke house, turkey house, and terraces facing southeast and south. n.d.
- List of Trees and Shrubs, using their Linnaean names, consisting of 31 plants, with a note about myrrh. n.d.
- Tirade against despotic rulers and their schemes, beginning with a quotation from David Hume, by [Thomas Mann Randolph?] n.d.
- Memoranda miscellany, including memoranda concerning bodies in motion; Latin poetry; a zoological note about the discovery of Richard Bradley concerning the distribution of the spawn of the pike fish; grafting plants; producing cherries; a method of bending planks of wood; the ultimate particles of matter; proof that there is a regular motion of the sap downwards as well as upwards in plants, which circulates much as blood does in animals; and definitions of shame and honor. n.d.